hello everyone this is
the active inference institute it is
guest stream number 15.2
on july 26 2022
we're here with bobby zarian and this is
going to be the second part of a
discussion that we opened some months
ago
and uh looking forward to it really
appreciate your visit and please just
set it up and continue however you see
fit i'll be documenting questions in the
live chat and looking forward a lot to
this discussion
okay thanks for having me
so uh the talk isn't quite uh what i
promised it's not part two i'd like to
come back in the future and talk about
you know that stuff um it's kind of
uh what i talked about last time but a
little bit more focused
uh more specific there was a recent
guardian article that came out that was
talking about whether there's this need
for a new evolutionary synthesis
we have the modern synthesis and then
the modern synthesis has been challenged
by the extended evolutionary synthesis
which includes more mechanisms things
that weren't recognized by
the modern synthesis so things like
epigenetics and
lamarckian mechanisms like the baldwin
effect uh multi-level selection or group
selection um so this is actually saying
that that's not radical enough
uh the integrated evolutionary synthesis
uh has that name because it integrates
evolutionary theory with uh
thermodynamics and information theory
and give gives us um
i think a much clearer picture of how
evolution works and why it's generating
complexity in the biosphere
so
originally this talk was also titled
something different it said a unifying
theory of reality
and yeah it's been kind of downgraded to
something a little less ambitious
because i did not have time to include
slides uh that talk about uh there's an
interpretation of quantum mechanics
called quantum darwinism
and a solution to the fine-tuning
problem
called cosmological natural selection so
what i'm trying to paint today is a
picture of a darwinian reality
and those uh paradigms are consistent
with this
darwinian framework
uh kind of a universal darwinism
type thing uh danned in it you know
comes to mind um so
this is just gonna focus on uh the
evolution of the biosphere the evolution
of life towards higher complexity and in
the future we can talk about all that
other stuff
awesome sounds good yeah um who would
you say this is for and how would you
like to update their cognitive model
yeah so
that's
i love that you put it that way yeah i
hope i'm updating people's model of
reality uh today so uh it's for the
active inference lab so it's a bit more
technical than you know it might be if i
was giving it to a general audience
but i tried to not get too technical at
the same time in my last talk i really
just talked about everything and um
used a lot of terminology that
uh i assumed that your audience would
know
today if anything's unclear
uh or you want um
uh me to go into a little bit more
detail uh please
feel free to
ask jump in i'll try to pause
um a few times
throughout the presentation and see if
anybody has any questions
because it's really this story of
evolution that's
something that you know you can tell as
a story um
and um you know i want people people to
understand the mechanisms better than
giving like the perfect presentation i
just want people to see how all of these
things
work together
um so it's from my book that just came
out a month ago
and that's available so if you like what
you hear
this is basically a kind of superficial
uh version of the content in part two of
the book
there's three parts so
there's this uh
kind of famous quote from dobzhansky who
did a lot of work uh creating the modern
synthesis
and the modern synthesis is basically
um
taking darwin's theory of natural
selection and updating it with a modern
understanding of genetics so it's not
really modern anymore i mean this was
like
you know the gene was uh dna was
discovered in the 50s and then in the
60s and 70s uh this was uh formulated
so he said nothing in biology makes
sense
in except in the light of evolution
i think it's a great statement i think
it's true
but the integrated evolutionary
synthesis uh says that doesn't go far
enough that nothing in biology or
evolution
makes sense except in light of
thermodynamics
and information
and shannon's information theory is
really the same theory as statistical
thermodynamics there's a lot of the same
formalisms
and we're gonna see
today that um
biological information
really the role of information
uh is that it allows life to sustain
itself against this tendency toward
decay described by the second law of
thermodynamics
and basically there's just one
evolutionary algorithm one mechanism
that is behind all this complexity
creation
and that has been called variation and
selection
uh that's a term from evolutionary
epistemology
which is based on the ideas of karl
popper
but it actually wasn't founded by karl
popper it was founded by a cognitive
psychologist named donald campbell
who was inspired by popper's view and
then popper contributed to it later
but the idea is that
variation and selection
the mechanism of evolution is
a form of trial and error learning
so evolution
adaptation is the same as learning it's
a learning mechanism and it creates
biological knowledge it creates
knowledge in the biosphere
um and david deutsch uh is one person
who has
written a lot about uh evolution as a
knowledge creation process and i think
that's
how we need to understand it from now on
and this is arguing that evolution does
have an arrow
or a direction
it is progressive
in other words
[Music]
in the 20th century stephen j gould was
very
adamant about killing this idea that
evolution is progressive
uh he you know saw it as
being teleological
um kind of implying that there's some
mystical force driving
uh evolution towards you know higher
levels of complexity
and i think that is wrong
um evolution is progressive but there's
no mystical force driving it
uh it is just mechanisms that are
completely
uh intelligible and
uh formalizable
so
and richard dawkins was one person who
uh
challenged gold on that he wrote a book
review uh about gold's book and
basically said that this idea that
evolution towards higher complexity was
this statistical illusion was wrong and
he cited uh
evolutionary transitions as being a
mechanism of complex degeneration and
we're going to talk about uh
evolutionary transitions today which is
left out of the modern synthesis they
don't talk about these transitions
this uh quote from stuart kaufman he
says there are things darwin couldn't
have known one of them was
self-organization in complex dynamical
systems if the new science of complexity
succeeds it will broker a marriage
between self-organization and selection
it'll be a physics of biology
so that's
part of what we're going to talk about
today uh how
self-organization
fits into the evolutionary picture
because it wasn't recognized by most
evolutionary biologists for a long time
and santa fe institute was one place
really you know doing
the complexity research that that
has made you know this mechanism of
self-organization
uh kind of famous um
it started off with uh the cyberneticist
so ross ashby
uh
had a principle of self-organization in
i think the 40s or 50s
so it's an old idea and it's you know
time that
uh i guess mainstream evolutionary
theory incorporates
self-organization into the picture and
we'll see that self-organization is
really the process that creates the
evolutionary transitions that i
mentioned
so we're going to start off with some
quotes just to give some context before
getting into the details
um
thomas huxley
a 19th century english biologist known
as darwin's bulldog for his advocacy of
evolutionary theory
said that the question of all questions
for mankind the problem which underlies
all others is more deeply interesting
than any other is the ascertainment uh
and of the place which man occupies
in nature
and of his relations to the universe of
things so what's our relationship to the
cosmos do we have one
is life
completely insignificant or could it
have
deep cosmic significance could it
influence the future evolution and
developmental trajectory of the universe
so here's
uh
one answer to that question the kind of
pessimistic answer man at last knows
that he is alone in the unfeeling
immensity of the universe
out of which he emerged only by chance
so this quote comes from jacques mono a
nobel prize winning french biochemist
a really smart guy
this book was really influential and
kind of painted this nihilistic picture
of reality
that was consistent with the
reductionist model of the world which
was you know the reigning view in the
20th century
and
today we're going to challenge that idea
uh christian de duve another nobel prize
winning biologist uh said that the
natural constraints within which chance
operates are such that evolution in the
direction of increasing complexity was
virtually bound to take place if given
the opportunity chance does not exclude
inevitability
so there's certain certainly
chance and contingency and randomness
operating in evolutionary processes you
have genetic mutation which is
at least partially a random blind
process
and uh
that's okay that doesn't mean the whole
thing is random so
there's a lot of evidence from
convergent evolution the work of simon
conway morris
that uh shows that uh
the certain
you know
designs organism designs are
regularities so we see them
uh emerge
kind of expectedly
so
david deutsch uh founder of quantum
computation and author of some great
books fabric of reality and his newer
the beginning of infinity said
narrowly conceived evolutionary theory
considers as mere vehicles for the
replication of our genes or memes and it
refuses to address the question of why
evolution has tended to create ever
greater adaptive complexity
or the role that such complexity plays
in the wider scheme of things
so you see
right here he was hinting at life which
he calls adaptive complexity
uh as
having this larger cosmic role
and i think adaptive complexity is a
great term
for life
uh kind of replacing the word life that
would be a good idea because life has
these mystical connotations so soon as
you say something like
life is in some sense some statistical
sense destined to spread
through the universe it sounds mystical
but when you say adaptive complexity
uh will spread um you get a lot less
groans because uh it makes it clear
that what life is is this phenomenon
that learns
living systems are complex adaptive
systems so adaptive complexity is just a
way to talk about the network of complex
adaptive systems that make up the
biosphere and once you learn that life
is really this phenomenon that is
continuously learning and
self-correcting
then you see why uh it's so robust and
why it seems like there is this
inevitability to evolution and life
getting off of its planet of origin
so we're going to kind of demystify that
process but in demystifying it we see a
natural process that is pretty mystical
as far as like
you know just
i i think it doesn't make sense to to
use the term
like to not say that there's not this
like kind of magical or mystical quality
of the process just because we can
understand it mechanistically
to me this paints a picture of nature
that's you know more wondrous than um
any sort of conception of nature that
involves like supernatural things i
think the the natural self-organizing
process
is as interesting as you know any
supernatural concept
um
and then you see this
really uh bold
quote by uh the great physicist freeman
dyson
who just passed away like a year or two
ago it is conceivable that life may have
a larger role to play
uh
sorry i can't see the quote then we have
yet imagined life may succeed against
all odds and molding the universe to its
own purpose
so we're gonna
see if um we can make an argument for
that
last quote paul davies says we now see
how it is possible for the universe to
increase both organization and entropy
at the same time
the optimistic and pessimistic arrows of
time can coexist the universe can
display creative unidirectional progress
even in the face of the second law
so nothing in this story
uh in any way violates the second law of
thermodynamics
um
and it's important that
you know that's emphasized because a lot
of people had this just superficial
interpretation of the second law that
the universe is growing increasingly
disordered on average over time
and uh
this presentation will say that that um
you know popular understanding uh of the
second law is wrong and that the
universe is becoming
more organized uh at the
largest scales okay
let's
get into it if anyone has any questions
about
um
[Music]
that introduction
nope okay so
the paradigm of emergence
and
cosmic evolution says each emergence in
the cosmic self-organization process
is brought together by a meta-system
transition or an evolutionary transition
that moves life further
away from a state of thermodynamic
equilibrium and total disorder through a
nested series of such phase transitions
where functional things come together to
make larger functional things which come
together to make even larger ones and so
on adaptive complexity becomes better
equipped to dominate the cosmos
life acquires an organization that is
increasingly hierarchical and integrated
and therefore more resilient and
computationally powerful
so this is
what that process looks like you see
this structure of hierarchy and
of matter which continues with the
hierarchy of life
uh so we're gonna show
how these new levels emerge and on the
right here you see that
uh there's this hierarchy of science
that has tried to
you know model this natural phenomenon
phenomena and you get these
levels that represent these different
emergencies so with biology we have life
then we have the emergence of mind and
we get psychology and then we have the
emergence of civilization
and we get culture
so
this framework says that and it's really
the framework of evolutionary
epistemology and universal darwinism it
says that the emergence and the
evolution of life mines society and
technology
are all part of one thermodynamic
process one evolutionary process one
computational process unified by the
concept of knowledge
and it says that humans are neither a
cosmic accident nor the end goal of
evolution
humans are a step on the evolutionary
ladder of becoming
and an essential driver of increasing
complexity
and it says the universe is undergoing a
grand and majestic self-organizing
process and at this moment in time in
this corner of the universe we are the
stars of the show
so
this is what
this process of cosmic evolution looks
like uh this comes from a book called
cosmic evolution by the harvard uh
astrophysicist eric chason
and
uh these are some unifying paradigms of
the past and present
so the integrated evolutionary synthesis
is not really a novel thing it's sort of
an update to
all of these uh unifying paradigms that
have come before it so general systems
theory
came out of cybernetics uh it was
founded by
ludwig von berdalanfi and
basically says that all complex systems
have similar organizing principles that
can be described conceptually and
modeled mathematically
the problem with this theory was that it
was a little too broad and not specific
enough
evolutionary epistemology
came after that and
it emphasizes that the evolutionary
process is a problem-solving procedure
that creates knowledge
so
the
growth of complexity
and the emergence of intelligence in the
biosphere arises out of a knowledge
accumulation process
in this view when i say knowledge
accumulation
uh this knowledge is encoded
in uh
the different forms of memory
um that life allows for so genetic
memory neural memory uh cultural memory
and we'll talk about that more later
universal darwinism came after
evolutionary epistemology was basically
the same theory though
um
so richard dawkins and dan din are
people that are associated with
universal darwinism and it emphasizes
that the universe is evolving at all
these different scales
and levels of complexity
so universal bayesianism is a term that
some people are using
and it's just basically an update of the
previous paradigms
so it basically says the same things
that you know now
evolution is the knowledge creation
process but it specifically says that
this knowledge is encoded in biological
systems
uh that knowledge is stored in the form
of a world model
and that the model is an internal
representation and statistical mapping
of the environment which gets updated
through adaptation and learning and
we're going to see that adaptation
is a form of learning and that learning
is a form of adaptation
so to kind of
frame this story earlier i said it's you
you can
tell the story in a kind of like
mythological
way so david deutsch says if one can
speak of a cosmic war
it's a war between monotony and novelty
between stasis and creativity
and in this war
our side is not destined to lose if we
choose to apply our unique capacity to
create explanatory knowledge we could
win
so it's a pretty uh
optimistic
uh
quote um and a story that i think you
know is probably a lot
more
comforting satisfying than the old view
that the universe is becoming
increasingly disordered and that life is
just
a transient uh phenomenon
we'll see that adaptive complexity uh
isn't transient
so
you could frame this as this
battle between order and disorder
or life versus entropy or knowledge
versus ignorance
and so the story starts with the second
law of thermodynamics which is kind of a
nice way to frame the evolutionary story
since the second law of thermodynamics
is this kind of iron-clad law that
everybody accepts
so it's kind of built on a really uh
firm theoretical foundation
so to understand life and its role in
cosmic evolution we have to understand
the second law which says that the
entropy of a system naturally increases
over time at least on average
you could sum this up by
the
quote things fall apart
so it's describing this tendency toward
decay and disorder
and we see that in this little simple
cartoon
below so in our everyday experience
things don't typically organize
themselves rooms get messier and
buildings erode
not the opposite
but
okay so yeah this is uh just a depiction
of that same process
uh which was the model that the
um
founder of the statistical interpret
interpretation of the second law
uh used so ludwig
boltzmann
um
imagined a simple system so an ideal gas
in a box
and you see that if this system
is just left to evolve over time
uh the these molecules spread out
simply because uh if they're just all
moving at random
um then there are
many more
configurations
that the system can be in that are
disordered compared to patterned
arrangements
so just due to this statistical tendency
uh you will get a system evolving toward
a more disordered state
if it's a closed system and
uh
there's no way for the system to access
any energy from the outside so
this is
you know this model
is looking at a gas in a box it's not
looking at the universe but people were
quick to jump uh to apply this to
the universe as a whole
under the assumption that the universe
is a closed system
uh but it ignores a lot of things so
this model ignored the effect of gravity
um because gravity doesn't really have
a noticeable effect on things that small
so it was just seen as negligible
and it also assumes that these particles
stay uncorrelated after they interact
and
[Music]
we know that with
you know certain chemical systems in
life the
molecules are had held together by
chemical bonds and forces
so
this model ignores a lot of things which
make it probably not very useful
to apply to the universe as a whole
and it leaves out this phenomenon
of life that we've called adaptive
complexity
so if uh
systems naturally become more disordered
than what's going on with life we see
life maintaining its structure and
you know re has the capability of
regenerating itself and making copies of
itself and producing all of this order
that we see around us in the biosphere
and uh
so adaptive complexity is this local
reversal of the second law
and schrodinger was one of the first
people to really
talk about this mystery
and
give us one piece of the puzzle
so life is able to
evade this tendency towards disorder
because
it is an open system
the planet is receiving
all of this free energy from uh the sun
and that energy
uh allows
us
an adaptive system to stay far from
thermodynamic equilibrium
so the trick to life evading the
tendency toward decay
is that it has the ability to extract
energy that allows it to do work
and that work is maintaining
its uh stable
non-equilibrium steady state
and uh so
you can think of
life
as
playing a game so the game of life
uh is this battle between order and
disorder so the challenge
that life has
that any system any adaptive system any
conceivable sentient system in any
universe
abiding by the second law
has this intrinsic problem and that's it
has to be able to resist the natural
tendency toward disorder which requires
work
so this intrinsic challenge gives life
an intrinsic goal
so
life does have a goal
and the goal is simply to continue to
persist to stay far from thermodynamic
equilibrium
or to survive
now
what
must life do in order to achieve that
goal it has to be able to extract energy
from the environment
and that's not a trivial task in order
to be able
to
navigate its environment
and actually extract or absorb this
energy
uh it has to acquire information
about the environment that it's in it
has to model the world
and um
life strategy is to search the space of
possible configurations
for structural and functional solutions
we call those adaptations to the problem
of survival
and so evolution is this process of life
exploring the design space and uh dennit
made this
way of looking at it popular in his book
darwin's dangerous idea
so on an abstract level we can imagine a
certain practical problem or challenge
as
so any challenge
we can imagine a challenge as having a
solution that exists somewhere out there
in the space of possibilities just
waiting to be found by adaptive
complexity so it may take some time but
if the possibility space the space of
possible solutions is continuously
explored in an efficient way eventually
a solution will be discovered
so darwinian evolution is a
problem-solving algorithm
and that algorithm is called variation
and selection
um yeah this slide was old i meant to
update that so this is supposed to show
that variation and selection is the
method of adaptation
and that uh this is a trial and error
learning process so trial and error is
the mechanism for learning those are the
same thing
so adaptation is equivalent to problem
solving is equivalent to learning
is equivalent to knowledge creation and
we're going to see a illustration of
that to make it a lot clearer
so
this is
an evolutionary epistemology inspired
picture that uh
david deutsch
supports so he says that
the whole scientific process resembles
biological evolution
a problem is like an ecological niche
and a theory is like a gene or a species
which is being tested for viability in
that niche
so
the way we should think about organisms
now is that they are embodied theories
about how to survive
in a particular niche
so a genome is basically a strategy for
survival
okay so this picture looks complicated
at first but it's pretty simple once you
break it down so here on the left
we see
you know one of the most simple
organisms we have a single-celled
organism
and this
says that
an adaptive system is an embodied theory
about how to stay far from equilibrium
and that basically it's searching for a
winning design
so a winning design is specifically one
that allows for energy extraction from
the environment
so now we're just really understanding
life as having to solve a thermodynamic
problem it has to find free energy
to maintain its non-equilibrium steady
state
and it does this without any
consciousness or conscious intent at
first
so let's imagine that this is the origin
of life that we start with this one
organism
it's a replicator so it makes copies of
itself and because genetic mutation is
unavoidable the copying process will
always make errors
then
you get a generation of new designs
that are variations
on the original design so here you see
design one two three
and four and
you can have as many designs as copies
that this organism can make
so just through replication with
mutation
you get this variation and selection
mechanism that will create learning
so natural selection
[Music]
is a filter
and natural selection
filters out the
dysfunctional designs
so
we see that uh
you could imagine that
so a bacterium
[Music]
some bacteria perform a process known as
chemotaxis so they will swim towards
molecular food and away from toxins
so they have some sort of
very basic abstract
world model of the environment some
statistical mapping that allows the
system to basically swim towards food
and away from threats
and you can imagine that this first one
maybe it swims in random directions it
doesn't
swim towards food yet it just moves
around randomly so it makes a copy of
itself let's say that copy
still has that
same behavior and
then you have another copy
let's say this one because of random
mutation swims toward poisons and away
from food
uh and this one third one just by chance
uh has a
a better design a more optimal design
where it swims towards food and away
from toxins
and you can imagine
you know however you know many types of
different designs with different
functions
and so some of these designs will die
out because they can't
fulfill this task of extracting energy
so they can't stay far from equilibrium
they get filtered out and this winning
design
gets to make copies of itself
and so
this winning design
is the one that can best predict its
environment
so it's the one that's best at
extracting energy
because it has the ability to predict
its environment
and so
this process continues
with a second iteration and it creates
this new generation of designs
and
again some of these designs will be
dysfunctional or at least not optimal
and
especially if they're competing uh
the
dysfunctional ones will die out so
natural selection acts as a filter again
and again we have another generation so
this iterative process
is how
basically the species design gets
optimized
and it is also a knowledge creation
process
because this organism
has a genetic code
that
codes for for these functional designs
or dysfunctional designs
and random
mutation
is creating
random bits of code it's creating like
random changes and
some of that code will
produce functional designs
so while it's producing all this
information
some of it is information that's not
predictive of the environment it's
useless information
the information
that survives the filter of natural
selection
has proved itself to be knowledge
and the reason i call the information in
these systems
that survive knowledge is because they
contain information
that reduces
the organism's uncertainty
regarding the environment
so you can look at this whole process
as basically a world model and there's
variations
being created to this you know embodied
uh internal model
and that
with these iterations the model is
getting updated
to
be
more accurate
so i'm not going to go into
active inference and free energy
principle and the bayesian brain
hypothesis here
but i will mention some things for
people who already are familiar with it
since this is the active inference
channel
that this whole process would be
minimizing free energy or prediction
error so as
adaptation occurs and you have these
different
generations the model
is getting updated in a bayesian fashion
and
john campbell has done work showing that
the evolutionary process is a process of
learning and specifically bayesian
inference and carl fristen
has worked with him on that
so i'm calling this knowledge the
information that encodes these uh
structures knowledge
that comes from evolutionary
epistemology
so what do i mean by that
so a dolphins streamline design which is
a product of the information stored in
its genome contains a knowledge of
hydrodynamics
and similarly an eagle's wing design
contains a knowledge of aerodynamics
so not only can we be certain that
engineers see knowledge in these
functional structures there should be
little doubt that these designs provided
the original inspiration for our
aircraft and submarine technology
so
um
yeah you
can think of evolution
as a knowledge creation process
and
um
you can think about all the species
that exist as being solutions to
different types of
environmental challenges
and so
humans
scientists studying these species can
learn a lot about
how
to
better manipulate the universe and
better solve our challenges by looking
at how
evolution has solved challenges in the
past
so
this process of adaptation that's
creating this knowledge is also creating
statistical correlation between the
organism and its environment
and
when you understand this you see that
natural selection
is something like an information channel
you could think of as pumping in
information from the environment into
life
uh life models its environment it's
isomorphic to its environment so
an organism
is a model of its environment in the way
that a key is a model of the locket
opens
so um as this
process that we see here
takes place and you have these different
iterations
of the adaptation process
it's becoming more correlated with its
environment
so we talked about these different
designs and
being different types of
bacteria some that
swim towards poisons and some that swim
away and towards food
and so we see
this is the work of physicist carlo
rivelli who is now interested in
evolution and how evolution creates
information
um his work builds on the work of david
wolpert and artem kochinski at the santa
fe institute
so
just to explain this concept of
adaptation creating statistical
correlation and
mutual information and this is really
what underlies uh its ability to predict
its environment
uh we have this simple example
so a well-adapted organism is one that
is statistically correlated with its
environment
so a bacterium that swims to the left
when nutrients are on the left and swims
to the right when nutrients are on the
right prospers a bacterium that swims at
random has less chances
so increasing statistical correlation
represents the creation of mutual
information and that comes from
shannon's uh
information theory
so basically
when
you have this correlation
uh
basically the information in these
organisms
is predictive of the environment and
this uh quote from fred dretzki who did
a lot of the pioneering work
applying information theory to uh
natural selection
this is from the biologist john maynard
smith's
essay on biological information
dretzki argues as follows if some
variable a is correlated with the second
variable b then we can say that b
carries information about a for example
if the occurrence of rain is correlated
with a particular cloud then the type of
cloud tells us whether it would rain
so we see here that adaptation equals
statistical correlation equals mutual
information
equals model optimization
equals knowledge creation
so
let me just skip some of this stuff
so we see how
knowledge is created uh
in this
example
and species are becoming
optimized for extracting energy in their
niche
but they're not becoming more complex
per se so
um since
an organism
is an embodied theory
about how to extract energy from the
environment it kind of follows uh ocam's
razor so uh it's really trying to be the
simplest solution to a thermodynamic
problem
so
at the beginning of this talk i i said
that this was going to explain
mechanisms of complexity generation and
this tendency towards higher
intelligence that we've seen
uh in our biosphere
um but it's not the case that
natural selection
is creating uh is making every species
more complex or more intelligent and
stephen j gould was right about that
uh if uh organism is extracting energy
and avoiding threats just fine in its
niche um it doesn't need to become more
complex
so crocodiles and sharks are
common examples
of um
organisms that haven't become more
complex over millions of years of
evolution
and there are examples like cave fish
that um
fish that you know weren't previously
existing in caves
uh got trapped in caves or some sort of
underground environment where
having eyes was no longer a selective
advantage you saw those organisms
actually become more simple
so
if evolution isn't creating
uh
is it making organisms more complex and
more intelligent
are certain species then what how do we
argue that intelligence is inevitable
like how does that work
so
it's not that evolution makes every
species more complex it's that evolution
will create a
new species and there will be this
growing ladder of complexity such that
the new species that emerge have to
solve more
complicated energy extraction problems
and that is uh basically what ratchets
up complexity so we're going to talk
about that now this tendency towards
intelligence
so we can think of each niche on earth
as a sort of energy slot a thermodynamic
slot for a given species
and an evolving population of organisms
efficiently searching the space will
discover a solution to a thermodynamic
problem that it didn't know existed
so the discovery of a novel energy
source or energy extraction technique is
both how a new niche and a new species
come into existence
so this darwinian evolution process
which is also called phylogenetic
learning this iterative learning um
process that's its generational
generational learning
um will naturally lead to speciation
because organisms will stumble upon ways
to exploit thermodynamic niches that
were previously inaccessible to life
purely for design reasons
so
let's look at that picture
one more time
so
when this organism self-replicates it's
making these different designs some of
them will be better at extracting that
source of energy for the first organisms
it was thought to be
the geochemic geochemical
energy uh that was around these
hydrothermal vents these deep sea
volcanoes
and um you can imagine
just by chance uh that it creates a copy
of itself and that it
discovers a configuration that can
suddenly
absorb sunlight
so that's how we get the generation of
photosynthetic bacteria
and when you get uh this you know new
source of energy unlocked
then uh
that bit is basically what creates a new
species
and
then
you don't just have this you know one
species exploring this
solution space
you have a growing uh problem space so
you will have
uh organisms discovering
new sources of energy
that weren't available so basically if
life is something like a game and it's
trying to
you know find these configurations that
are best at predicting the environment
it'll kind of just by chance you know
discover that there's like a
different aspect of the game so there
it will unlock a new
uh source of free energy uh which
creates a new
species
and a new niche
okay so
just to
make that idea a little more clear
there's a great paper called the energy
expansions of evolution by olivia judson
and she says the history of the life
earth system can be divided into five
energetic epochs each featuring the
evolution of life forms that can exploit
a new source of energy these sources are
geochemical energy sunlight oxygen flesh
and fire
the first two are present at the start
but oxygen flesh and fire are all
consequences of evolutionary events
since no category of energy source has
disappeared this has over time resulted
in an expanding realm of the sources of
energy available to living systems and a
con commitment increase in the diversity
and complexity of ecosystems
so why do increasingly intelligent
species emerge so first we have these
organisms around the hydrothermal vents
i mentioned reductive chemoautotrophs
there are solutions to the problem of
how to extract energy from geochemical
gradients
uh photosynthetic bacteria
the single-celled ancestors of plants
are a solution to the problem of how to
extract work from all the solar energy
that was flowing through the planetary
system
and heterotrophic organisms then emerge
which are organisms that eat other
organisms and their solution to the
problem of how to extract energy from
life itself
and this explains how intelligence
emerges
because once life starts having to model
life
other agents with causal power and
adaptive behavior the computational task
of extracting free energy gets
increasingly difficult as increasingly
complex species arise
by virtue of having to model each other
the complexity of some species gets
ratcheted up by what's known as an
evolutionary arms race
so
here i'll mention this law from
cybernetics
created by ross ashby called the law of
requisite variety
and applied to evolution it basically
says that
an adaptive system must have as many
states like cognitive states behavioral
states as there are challenges
in its environment
and so when you have this process of
new species emerging
uh that are able that basically discover
configurations that allows them to
extract a new source of energy or eat a
new source of energy
you get this
pressure towards or this tendency
towards species
that
have a larger repertoire of cognitive
states
and so they can deal with more
challenges
and so this increases uh an agent's
empowerment
that's a term from the computational
neuroscience literature
um harvard ai researcher alex wisner
gross has this concept of
a causal entropic force but basically we
can see that uh
the biosphere as a whole
is increasing uh its repertoire
of internal states
and the most complex species
is also um
[Music]
possessing a repertoire of
inter of larger internal
states and this
is
one explanation for this tendency
towards higher intelligence
so
just to reiterate those points once more
why has the evolutionary record shown a
trend of the emergence of increasingly
complex forms
when all conceivable niches on the earth
were filled that wasn't the end for
complexification new species create new
niches because the free energy slot they
provide is themselves so they become
food
for any sort of other organism
that through blind variation and natural
selection
discovers a configuration
that allows them to
exploit that new source of food
so the cyberneticist francis heiligin
said it is well documented by
evolutionary biologists that ecosystems
tend to become more complex a number of
different species increases and the
number of dependencies in other
languages linkages between species
increases
yale wilson said not only do ecosystems
contain typically lots of niches that
will eventually be filled by new species
there is a self-reinforcing tendency to
create new niches
and stu kaufman uh actually
has shown this parallel between
uh niche emergence and
the auto catalytic process that we see
um with basically
the precursor to life was this chemical
auto catalytic set so
um
stu kaufman says ecosystems are auto
catalytic
auto catalytically closed
self-sustaining reaction networks that
reliably drive up biological diversity
and complexity as they self-amplify and
evolve
okay so that tells us how we get species
of increasing intelligence but it
doesn't answer everything about how that
happens because it isn't telling us
how
you go from single-celled organisms to
multicellular organisms
and it's not addressing
um
the complexity that we see with these
collectives with society so how do we go
from multi-cellular organisms to these
larger societies
and
we've seen that because of the internet
uh that human societies have become
integrated into this larger
computational network that some have
called a global brain
because humans are basically nodes
exchanging information in the same way
that
um neuronal populations or neurons are
exchanging information in the brain
so
we need to talk about more than normal
uh darwinian evolution competitive
evolution
and uh we need to
include self-organization in this model
so before i start talking about
self-organization and that will kind of
be the second half of this
and it's a bit shorter
any questions about
any of the mechanisms that have been
presented so far
yeah there's definitely a few questions
would you like me to ask them now or do
you think it makes more sense to just
present everything you'd like to get out
and then we can have just a full q a
uh if the questions are like
broad questions that aren't um
specifically asking about like the
mechanisms that were just described then
we could wait but if it's about this
stuff maybe it'd be good to talk about
now
let's um go through the whole
presentation and again i'll have um
compiled questions by then thank you
okay
great
all right so this is that
same
thing that we were looking at earlier
um it was an older version looks a bit
different of these arrows but yeah this
is showing the same process this uh
phylogenetic learning process that
happens through
competitive evolution so this is you
know normal
darwinian evolution
but you see here at the bottom this part
at the bottom right
is showing that
these
organisms down here these different
designs they don't have to compete
they can cooperate they can find a
synergistic collective configuration and
form a larger unit
and so
this is
this
is the process of self-organization
right here
and basically that creates a new level
of complexity
so if you think of life as a game and
it's this game where life's trying to
you know life's exploring the design
space looking for configurations that
solve its thermodynamic problem of
staying far from equilibrium
this process of self-organization is how
life graduates to a new level in the
game
so you don't always have to compete you
can cooperate
and
we're going to talk about
self-organization as a darwinian process
this marriage of self-organization and
selection that stu kaufman
uh talked about in that quote at the
beginning
so richard dawkins says darwin's
survival of the fittest is really a
special case of a more general law of
survival of the stable
and this concept of evolution being
about survival of the stable
will allow us to understand how
self-organization is a darwinian process
and by a darwinian process
i mean that it works through the
evolutionary algorithm that we've called
variation and selection
so
here you see
that
the self-organization process up top
there's just a couple examples of
collectives
of
higher level systems that are made of
many units so it can be a collection of
molecules
forming something like an auto catalytic
set
or it can be a collection of agents it
can be people in a society
but basically
this is the evolutionary process it
works through variation and selection
because uh to
have variation
on a design or structure
um you don't need replication you don't
need a system that's making copies of
itself that
makes the process
uh more efficient in ways
but you can have a single system that's
exploring a variety of internal
configurations
and so you see this flow chart here
where it says system blindly explores
various configurations in the space of
possible designs via trial and error so
it's just being pushed by a flow of
energy
with humans we're powered by metabolism
so
um
it's still a flow of energy pushing us
technically and
uh it's basically
causing the system to randomly explore
different states in the configuration
space
now those configurations that it
discovers that allows the system to
extract sufficient energy to stay out of
equilibrium are the ones that get
retained and the system is able to
persist for longer
so
it's the same variation and selection
mechanism but here since there's only
one system
donald campbell the inventor of
evolutionary epistemology
being influenced by the cyber
cyberneticists
called this blind variation and
selective retention
so the stable states
are selectively selectively retained
so those states that the system moves
into
that does not allow the system to
persist
uh are filtered out
so really you can explain evolution with
this simple kind of tautological phrase
uh what works persists and
it
that dawkins
um simplification
of darwin's
law as uh really being about the
survival of the stable
shows us why this
integrated evolutionary synthesis is
important
we can see the second law's tendency
toward disorder as being a selection
pressure it's the second law that
filters out the unstable designs
and they're not just filtering out the
unstable designs
it's specifically
filtering out
designs that are
less functional so the stable designs
because of this
constraint this thermodynamic constraint
that that systems must be able to
extract energy to maintain their order
uh
it is really discovering
the most functional designs the designs
that are best at predicting the
environment
and the designs
that are
uh most robust and most functional
so
this process explains the origin of life
so you have all these interacting
components these are molecules the
molecules
that are involved in organic chemistry
and
um jeremy england who did this work when
he was at mit
named this process dissipative
adaptation
so he was showing how basically a flow
of energy pushing a system of molecules
far from thermodynamic equilibrium
will lead to this
uh
increasingly ordered state because the
system is exploring configurations
and
finding those information getting stuck
basically in the configurations that
allow the system to extract and
dissipate more energy
so
uh
the book
discusses this principle of recursive
self-organization
it was the name was inspired by
ross ashby's principle self-organization
but this is
basically explaining why
interacting agents will consistently
link up to form stable holes
and that's because working together
allows the individual systems to extract
more energy with less work
so there's this effect that has been
called synergy
so
nature promotes cooperation because it's
thermodynamically beneficial for all
parties and for that reason
synergistic collective configurations
will eventually be discovered by a mini
component system that's exploring
various states or configurations through
the blind variation and selective
retention mechanism
so agents will compete until they
discover that working together makes
everyone's task easier
and this is a lesson for humanity
because um
the the challenges the sustainability
challenges which is an entropy problem
can only be solved these global
sustainability challenges can only be
solved if we work together
working together increases the
computational power
of the system so
um
it's it's
self-organization i guess
i think was kind of ignored by
evolutionary biologists for a long time
because
they
they didn't want to recognize anything
that sounded like a teleological
mechanism like something like kind of
mystical and it was like how
you know there's a second law of
thermodynamics how can there be
spontaneous self-organization
well the answer was it's not exactly
spontaneous it requires energy flowing
through the system
pushing the system far from equilibrium
and forcing it to
explore the configuration space
and that's how we see that it's a
darwinian process that you it explores
these different configurations and the
configurations that are most functional
are the ones that uh
survive and
pass the the filter of natural selection
so
here's just
uh illustration showing
that self-organization
is something that can happen at all of
these levels
so
uh complex adaptive systems are nested
systems they're systems made of
smaller systems that are interacting
and
they
they build
on one another so you have
single-celled organisms coming together
to form this multi-cellular unit like a
slime mold
you know humans are multicellular
organisms that come together and make
societies
uh you have ant colonies here which do
the same and so these
form a collective unit
that function very much
like the units that they're made of
so you see that adaptive systems can
exist in all these levels
and these adaptive systems have similar
dynamics and work through this these
same variation and selection mechanisms
and that's how they evolve toward
increasing robustness
and complexity
and computational power
i'm jeffrey west's book scale
this great book about that
so this principle of recursive self
organization says that as long as a
biosphere is creating a growing variety
of complex adaptive systems
some of those systems will interact to
produce higher level complex adaptive
systems will which will come together to
form even larger complexes
this process continues at higher and
more computationally sophisticated
levels as time marches on familiar
examples of superorganisms include ant
colonies termite mounds human societies
and the ecosystems that make up the
biosphere
and all of these distributed networks
process information and fight to
maintain their organization in ways that
are surprisingly similar to the
organisms they're made of
so it tells us that knowledge of the
dynamics and mechanisms at one level can
be informative of isomorphic phenomena
at other levels
so it's kind of interesting here because
you see that this theory has predictive
power that no reductionist model has
this you know reductionist model where
it's trying to look trying to understand
reality and predict reality by looking
at this most base level such as the
interactions of like basic particles
and forces
don't give us this predictive power that
this uh paradigm does because it
basically says that we can use
adaptive systems we can look at those
patterns
at one level and then we can use that to
understand things that might not be easy
to see
at another level
so for example
um and this we saw that paper with stu
kaufman saying that ecosystems were auto
catalytic sets setting auto catalytic
sets can tell us about ecosystem
dynamics and vice versa
uh studying human brains can tell us
about the emerging global brain
so this is something that you know
i won't go into here maybe in the next
talk
um but
there's this question of if there is a
global brain
is a global mind emerging
could the global mind even be like a
conscious mind
uh and
i think that something at this paradigm
uh some sort of predictive power that it
has
would say that for that mind to emerge
the system might have to
duplicate
the
dynamics that you see
underlying conscious brain states so not
all brain states are conscious states
when you go to sleep before you enter a
dream there are periods where
consciousness ceases to be
but the brain state is still functioning
physiologically it's keeping you alive
so um to understand
how a global mind emerges from a global
brain
uh we would we probably want to look at
how
we probably want to look at like human
brains and looking at this transition
between unconscious to conscious states
um and every level has novelty
and so they're not going to be exactly
the same
new properties will emerge so
it's not certain that
these predictions will tell you
everything about the higher level that
hasn't emerged but it will give you a
sort of
outline of the dynamics that
could be really useful
so this rep process of recursive uh
self-organization creates this
hierarchical emergence
that we saw at the beginning
now we see exactly why it happens these
things come together
these units come together to make larger
units because cooperating makes the
thermodynamic task of staying far from
equilibrium
uh
easier
and
uh you get the emergence of new
properties
as these higher level emerge uh higher
levels emerge
and so with brains which is
left out of this
but uh with the emergence of brains you
have a system that
can encode
the causal consequences
of its actions in real time
and
that allows the system to create a
variable for itself before brains
an organism that does something like
interacts with the environment there's
no synaptic plasticity there's no
mechanism for
creating a memory of the effects on that
environment in real time
and so what brains allow is the system
to
um
encode the consequences of its actions
which gives it an understanding of
itself it's really the beginning of
self-modeling
and so
something that's in addition to
um this concept of intelligence being
about like the the size of the
repertoire of mental states
which is increased by this niche
emergence process that we discussed
you also need to think about these
levels of awareness that come from
self-reference in the form of
self-modeling
um so that would be for
another talk where we talk about like
how does consciousness emerge from this
um
but yeah i just wanted to point out that
these levels of awareness
uh are another important factor
uh of the emergence uh and growth of
intelligence
uh that we can't leave out
um
and it's an emergent property so
this process of multi-level
self-organization
and recursive emergence is creating more
complex structures these
you know
hierarchical adaptive systems and these
systems are
these evolutionary transitions are also
revolutions in information
storage and processing machinery
so we start out with genetic material
and
then brains emerge and we have neural
memory that sits on top of the genetic
memory
and then we have collective form
and then we get cultural memory
so memory that's shared among all the
brains of the individuals in the system
and then we get
things like books and journals
and then eventually
technological memory digital memory
so you can see
that
this process uh
is a process of knowledge accumulation
and that the biosphere
and technology the technosphere you
could call it
this is all one continuous process
i didn't talk about it here but one of
the big insights of karl popper's
evolutionary epistemology
was that science
and adaptive learning all work through
this variation and selection mechanism
so it's called trial and error learning
in the developmental psychology
literature
and
you can understand science as
um
competing theories
uh
that that works through like this
darwinian process and the mechanism he
used the name for that was called
conjecture and refutation
but it's it's all trial and error
learning it's all variation and
selection
you have these different models and then
these models get tested and natural
selection weeds out the
models that aren't predictive of the
environment
so
what does the integrated evolutionary
synthesis show us this theory of
knowledge creation
it shows us that knowledge is power
so this utor was just an acronym for
unifying theory of reality
uh shows us that knowledge is power
is not just a hollow buzz phrase from
the digital age it's true in the most
fundamental way
uncertainty reducing information is
life's first and last weapon in the
ongoing war with disorder and it infuses
organic matter with control and causal
power
without knowledge life cannot exist for
more than a moment much less colonize
the galaxy and beyond
this suggests that setting out on the
path toward cosmic superiority is not a
choice that intelligent agents like homo
sapiens make upon careful reflection nor
is it just some quirky ambition we
stumbled onto by chance
humanity's collective desire to
transcend mortality and expand outward
into space
so
apparent from our current scientific and
technological endeavors
emerges not incidentally but as an
inevitable consequence of the fact that
continual knowledge acquisition is a
fundamental biological imperative
so
the sun is our source of energy it's
what allows us to stay far from
equilibrium
intelligent species that are modeling
the world with increasing sophistication
will realize that there's this
thermodynamic game clock
that if life is to persist in the long
term it has to leave the planet
so
spacex like isn't
elon musk's like creative idea this is
an imperative
that any
sufficiently intelligent species
uh will recognize
and this
has hopefully shown how natural
selection is an information channel that
pumps information from the inanimate
world into life
and through that process nature begins
modeling itself so matter starts
finding a configuration and that allows
it to model
the world around it that it's part of
so it's encoding its own structure
reality is encoding its own structure
and the universe begins to wake up
so
some of the other wording was you know
life ascending to this you know cosmic
superiority and being able to dominate
the cosmos but you can similarly look at
this
whole story
not as a battle between life and entropy
and order
and disorder but that those things are
complex complement complementary
so they sort of need each other and they
work together
and so
it's not
the case that life is
dominating the cosmos it's that the
universe itself is self-organizing
through this process um and that
basically
uh life is and agents are these kind of
sensory modalities
for the universe
i think it's
uh appropriate to to look at it that way
i don't think there's anything
wrong with it um
so here's a
quote from harold morwitz who was
a founding member of the santa fe
institute
uh he was a professor of mine and it was
a big inspiration
on the book
he says we start with observations and
if evolving if the evolving cosmos has
an observed direction rejecting that
view is clearly non-empirical
there need not necessarily be a knowable
endpoint but there may be an arrow
and so christoph koch
one of the world's most respected
neuroscientists
wrote the rise of sentient life within
times wide circuit was inevitable teohar
deschardin is correct in his view that
islands within the universe if not the
whole cosmos are evolving toward ever
greater complexity and self-knowledge
the universe is a work in progress the
evidence from cosmology biology and
history is compelling
so we're seeing a kind of change in
sentiment and it's been brewing for a
long time
but that this
idea this paradigm of the universe being
self-organizing and becoming
increasingly complex
is
completely scientific and
i think
given what we know
it is um
it has predictive power too we can
understand we can predict things about
future emergencies so i would like to
see
this uh paradigm of emergence
replace the uh reductionist paradigm
and
where is this taking us so this is a
kind of far out speculation but i think
you know given the story told so far
it's okay to go here um paul davies
super respected
uh theoretical physicist says
many scientists have
sorry i can't see that whoops
there was stuff over the text
many scientists have speculated that as
the timeline stretches toward infinity
so an emerging super intelligence will
become more and more godlike so that in
the final stage
um
the sorry i can't see that the mind will
emerge
with the
sorry about that that's kind of
anti-climactic for me to mess up here
so that in the final stage the supermind
will merge with the universe mind and
cosmos will be one he goes on then the
whole character of the universe
including the emergence of its laws and
the nature
of
of its state sorry of its states become
inextricably intertwined with
mentality with its mindfulness
and
so
what would that look like this is from
where occurs while the singularity is
near
where it shows this trajectory where uh
life creates technology and it merges
with technology and you get the universe
waking up
what about heat death
uh does does this process happen and
then fade out because the universe is
going towards thermodynamic equilibrium
well people like stu kaufman and david
deutsch
have challenged the heat death uh
scenario
more and more physicists are with
different you know alternative models
but
some of these models basically say
uh
that the expanding universe
um allows for
a
continual free energy supply
um
i will get into that in another talk uh
but yes so where is this heading um
maybe something like this maybe
something like a cosmic mind can't rule
that out
and uh yeah this comes from that book uh
the almighty carl fristen was nice
enough to give me
a blurb for it
if you email uh the romance of reality
if you buy it from amazon and or
wherever and send me a screenshot of the
receipt with your address
i'll send you a signed numbered book
plate it's like a sticker that goes
inside the book
and yeah thank you so much for having me
again
nice
thank you very much bobby
okay
let's take a deep breath and then to the
question and answer
yeah
awesome
okay
wow a lot there so i'm just going to ask
some questions that were asked in the
live chat during the stream and also
just some other ones i wrote down
okay
so i'd like to start with one of the
first parts of the stream you read the
dabjansky quote nothing in biology makes
sense except in the light of evolution
so famous and memeable quote
yeah my question was
what else
is necessary and or sufficient for sense
making in biology like is evolution the
only light or what what are the lights
that help us
bring light to those issues so first
part is about what else is necessary or
sufficient and the second part is
how should we move forward
knowing um
what is necessary to make light of
evolution
well i guess it depends on how you
define evolution because some people
might be defining evolution very
narrowly in terms of like the modern
synthesis and someone might say we need
to understand self-organization we need
to understand emergence but with this
framework all of those things are
included under the umbrella
of evolution
so i'd say that you need
evolution to understand
the generation of complexity
and intelligence
um but
you need these you know it needs to be
expanded to include these
ideas uh about um multi-level
emergence and uh this process where you
have like self-modeling so we need to
understand like
how self-reference fits into this
picture
brains allow
self-modeling and um
you know first you have the emergence of
consciousness which in this definition i
would be talking about you know
subjective awareness not necessarily
like self-awareness or self-conscious
um so self-awareness would be a higher
level of self-reference
so um those
basically that
to explain all of this stuff
the evolutionary model would have to be
this model of cosmic evolution where you
talk about you know
adaptation through darwinian competitive
evolution but you also have this
cooperative evolution
with self-organization creating these
new emergencies and these emergencies
bringing about new properties new causal
powers and
higher levels of awareness
but uh you know it's
i don't want to be it's like
reductionistic to be like is it all
evolution so i think it's
important a lot of trends today you're
seeing like
whiteheads process ontology coming back
and this understanding of you know
systems as processes rather than things
i think that's enlightening
um
i think that
we need to
talk about philosophy and
metaphysics even um so
for example
and i talked about this in my last talk
but we need to think about you know is
hard determinism true or is
reality a little bit more complex where
reality
fundamentally has this probabilistic
element
at the lowest level but then
you know these higher level systems
emerge
uh with you know these deterministic
trajectories and
um
you get uh
yeah so so
because the the model the hard
determinism model that comes kind of
from this laplacian model of reality
this idea that there's just particles
following these trajectories
it has
metaphysical
uh and philosophical implications like
we have no agency that there's just one
future and it's completely determined
and if we had a powerful enough computer
we could even predict that turns out
that that's wrong
and uh
this new model uh allows for true agency
and it allows for um
[Music]
organisms that emerge that have
something like free will and
that term opens up a different bag of
worms um that's like some you know i'd
like to talk about that in the next
presentation but when i say free will
i'm
talking about
biological agency and the fact that
organisms
making decisions um
we're not just particles following
trajectories we're actually
cybernetic control units
um
that have emerged through these
evolutionary processes that i explained
this time um basically those
processes that are
pumping information into the system
that information
gives agents causal power such that you
will see
systems behave very differently than
inanimate systems so an inanimate system
like a rock
only moves if it's pushed by a force but
living systems because they metabolize
and store energy they have
self-generated motion and they're not
predictable
with classical mechanics
you have to have some sort of higher
level theory like
fristen's bayesian brain hypothesis the
free energy principle
so you ca it's not that organisms aren't
predictable at all uh you can actually
predict what they will do based on
saying for example that they're going to
behave in a way that minimizes their
model's prediction error
and that's very different than trying to
calculate what the system's going to do
based on these based on microphysics
first of all you can't do it second of
all i'm saying that that that idea is
uh misguided to begin with
because um this process where natural
selection pumps information into these
adaptive systems creates systems that
have uh what
people like sarah walker and paul davies
have called informational control so it
creates these cybernetic systems which
use feedback mechanisms to stay far from
equilibrium and we can't understand
causality without understanding the role
that information plays in biology
so
yeah
[Music]
evolution can explain a lot but it
requires us to
talk about thermodynamics and
information and really what information
allows
systems to do is to continue to persist
in the world against this tendency
towards decay
okay i've noted it down i have uh causal
powers free will agency the role of
information evolution energy
thermodynamics for the part three
so
let's uh leave a little footnote there
um
i wanted to add a few kind of resonances
that i saw with active inference like
places where there was a nice
plug-in or like a saddle point between
the way that you framed it just in this
nice presentation and in some of the
ways that
people are modeling in active inference
today
so you
provided a dawkins quote with survival
of the stable and that is kind of like
a operational
definition
for the related claim survival of the
fittest and people sometimes say well
that's circular and survival of the
stable almost says like it steps into
that circularity it's like yes in fact
it is that way
and that's
what our operational definition is
repeated measurements
is going to be what a thing is over a
given time scale so there might be some
spatial or temporal scale where a
gradient or a boundary or a blanket does
exist
but that's going to be like an observer
and a relational
specific situation rather than like an
all or none question about what kinds of
things and processes exist so um just
wanted to give that one and then i have
a few more but what do you what do you
think about that like where does this
survival of the stable
come in and how do you think that's
different than how sometimes people have
framed evolution and ecology in the past
so yeah there is this criticism of the
survival of the fittest being this kind
of tautological hollow statement because
what's you know what survives
is what's fit but what's fit and you
define it as what survives so you're not
really getting to the bottom of it
but this that's one
thing
that's one of the like i guess
highlights of this integrated synthesis
is we get an answer to that
um and you're right saying what's stable
you know it actually kind of embraces
that thing like what what works persist
or what's stable persists kind of has
that same problem but the thermodynamic
uh perspective
um
gives it a specific answer it says what
is stable is what's able to extract
energy from the environment
so it's what's functional so we finally
have an answer to like what fitness is
that isn't tautological it's
it's a system's ability to extract
energy to stay far from equilibrium
but also avoid threats because if
something kills you it's going to
rupture the markov blanket and you are
going to collapse to equilibrium you're
going to die
so yeah
the
the answer to like what fitness is is
this ability to evade thermodynamic
decay
okay
thank you let me go to the next one of
these resonances because again i really
liked how it was
laid out and i guess how many
paths we walked around some
core points you mentioned learning and
adaptation
and seeing those
in a new light like on part of a new
continuum and so that's a lot like an
active inference how there's similarity
in how perception is modeled and in how
slower and even slower processes of
learning and memory happen
and all of that is framed as a type of
parameter
finding
whether that's what organisms are doing
which is realism that's one perspective
or whether it's just a way that we can
model organisms that's another
perspective instrumentalism so like when
the perception of the ball crossing the
visual field is happening
is that perception of the location
especially if we think from this
generative uh approach like the bayesian
brain
is it perception yes is it learning the
parameter like in a technical sense like
machine learning of a parameter is it
learning the parameter representing the
location also yes so there's kind of a
connection between
learning and adaptation
and
because data
and observations coming in through the
blanket
are sometimes like sparse
conflated related through causal
mechanisms that aren't directly observed
all these challenges with them
evolution shapes systems ability
for their for their sense making
with the statistical regularities of the
niche
and that's been something that has been
approached from people
outside of the free energy principle
active inference
just um
from different angles for example like
collective behavior
with the work of debra gordon and
thinking about how collective behavior
evolves to be fitting statistical
regularities of different niches like
four ant colonies like you mentioned
and then also on the other hand this
uh imperative to be fitting
literally the statistical regularities
of the niche leads directly to the
embedded and the inactive
all the four e's etc
and then the kind of piece that ties
that all together is you talked about
the need to extract free energy like in
a chemical
sense
in a dissipative situation you need to
extract
chemical free energy liberatable work
from the environment
and then in order to navigate the
uncertainty at higher and higher levels
more and more planning has to come into
play
and then that is like modeled with
variational free energy
in active inference which isn't exactly
like that liberatable biochemical energy
but it seems to be in people interpreted
differently but
they over they overlap in certain
situations because the systems that are
planning well are planning well to
extract energy the systems that are not
planning well are not succeeding at
extracting effective energy so like
there is a relationship even though
those variables are not formally the
same
yes yeah very cool so
um
[Music]
yeah it's it's this story of free energy
that the active inference paradigm is
explaining but it becomes literal
so
minimizing information theoretic free
energy or predictive model error
is exactly what allows the system to
minimize actual
thermodynamic free energy so if you look
at the biosphere as a whole system you
can look at individual agents individual
organisms or these collectives
maxwell ramstead and first in have done
work showing that you know at these
talking about complex adaptive systems
that our societies these things are
minimizing free energy as well um
so yeah basically
um you have this story
this kind of neat little story where you
can explain it all in terms of like
different types of entropies
so
life is trying to keep internal entropy
low
and to do that it needs to extract free
energy um but by extracting free energy
it's dissipating more of the world's
free energy supply so it's keeping
internal entropy low
and increasing external
entropy
and it does that by minimizing
its prediction error and that's
minimizing shannon entropy or
uncertainty or ignorance
so
yes um i think
what one kind of goal of this you know
integrated synthesis
is to
basically it can incorporate the
the free energy principle
um
because uh to minimize
um actual thermodynamic free energy to
stay far from equilibrium
you have to minimize your uncertainty of
the environment and that's what you know
bayesian inference
is doing
and
so
um
there's one other point i was going to
make about that
yeah well yeah so um
i mean the free energy principle i think
on its own you know it's just saying
that systems will minimize uh you know
the model's prediction error but it
doesn't talk about like how you get like
more complex species or anything it
doesn't really tell us this whole story
of evolution it just talks about
minimizing free energy so
uh what this story does
is starts to get us think about uh
thinking about niches
and um that each niche uh represents
this set of challenges
and the set of computational problems
and that um
uh systems uh basically when you want to
think about like why complexity
increases
um
well so
minimizing free energy like trying to
reduce surprise
uh
will
keep you um far from equilibrium only
for so long
so if the environment changes
then that species will die that species
will get filtered out by natural
selection so
um there is a benefit to being curious
there's a benefit to seeking out
surprise
and that's because um basically
um if you can find a new
niche to exploit then you don't have to
compete
with uh everyone else in the species or
whatever group that is
so
it's not just about minimizing
surprise in in in
many cases um
you know a more complex species
the most complex species especially like
humans
it's beneficial
to
um
be curious and do epistemic foraging
and try to you know imagine
the space of possible configurations
where society is headed so there's this
um
[Music]
real benefit uh
to to seeking out new knowledge
that i think the free energy principle
may kind of leave out or hint at
awesome
thanks for sharing that just to add a
few more points
um so you mentioned
daniel dennett's 1995 book darwin's
dangerous idea
and one of the really memorable parts in
that book
is this distinction between the cranes
and the sky hooks and the images like a
building is constructed and then we're
going to see the artifact but not the
process of how it was made and then ask
like
was this likely constructed by a crane
that put the last windows on the top or
put the last piece of um you know
building on top or was there a skyhook
that
built kind of a castles in the sky
and then built down
and um
the constructivist answer just a
construction site but like a biological
constructivist answer which is to say
like a developmental perspective it's
like well it was cranes all the way down
and smaller cranes are basically
constructing larger cranes if needed and
then at some level there's like some um
way for the seething of tiny tiny cranes
somehow to facilitate larger cranes
arising um so i was reminded of the
cranes and skyhooks and and then as you
just brought up in that light dance last
answer and in some of the figures
the design approach
connects us with that kind of darwinian
constructivism that dennett laid out
but also you connected that to
process ontology
and
that in a sense this
constructivism
this niche constructivism
and the way that the bottom of forces
are leading to increasingly powerful
large-scale
organizations of systems like whether we
call it life or adaptive complexity like
you laid it out
um
i'm seeing a sort of
omega point direction
towards
instead of like finite competition
curiosity driven niche
creation
for certain systems or
maybe something involving other scales
where like there's a rebalancing of
the relevance of different mechanisms
because we're seeing
the adaptive complexity process playing
out
in a different way but that was what i
was thinking and wondering how this
framing influences how we act
yeah so i think um
uh it basically demystifies what looks
like a teleological process
and i still think it's okay to call it
teleological because it is goal directed
but it's not teleological the way some
you know theologians
have used it to mean that there's this
mystical force or something like
well it's really interesting it gets
into like language issues because like
uh henry bergson who uh coined that term
elon vitale and tiohar de chardin who
had a similar
concept of radial energy and even going
back to aristotle and his intellecki um
in tilos um these people claim to be
talking about something natural even
teal hard and
uh so what we're seeing is that you can
have this directional evolutionary
process
uh without there being any mystical
force so
it's
you know it's not the case where we're
demystifying everything and then getting
you know because we got rid of this
teleological force we show that it
doesn't exist this mystical
you know
immaterial force like pushing
things toward progress
uh by showing that doesn't exist
we're not
killing the argument that evolution is
progressive we're actually
showing that this idea can exist
in a completely naturalistic framework
and to me it makes it more interesting
but you do clearly see this statistical
tendency towards higher intelligence and
not only that
evolution advances at a rate that allows
life to leave the planet before
its star dies and that's specifically
because
the process
creates consciousness and
higher levels of awareness
that um basically create this imperative
in the uh
most intelligent species of a biosphere
such that they understand that long-term
persistence
requires getting off the planet
so um
yeah
it is the case that that a lot of
species just evolved to be um
as complex as their niche and if they're
getting their energy uh just fine like
bacteria there's no reason
for there to be any pressure towards
higher complexity but with humans for
example
we start to construct our environment we
construct niches we build all of this
order around us
and we create these new selection
pressures and we create all of these new
biologically relevant variables so
there's a tendency where the most
complex species
uh basically how many variables they
have to model is open-ended and anyone
who is willing
to
kind of go beyond
um
you know
the amount of things that most people
model
is going to have some sort of advantage
let me make that a little bit more clear
so someone
in some very simple let's say small
rural rural conservative town i'm not
saying that in a bad way but um you can
imagine a you know a culture with a
simple lifestyle
it might not be
um
adaptive to be someone like roger
penrose like some freak genius i think i
read that like pinrose gets like
lost like walking around like
his office and stuff like he's just
really absent-minded because his head's
probably in the clouds thinking about
mathematics
he might not
do well he might even be considered like
the towns like crazy person in a small
conservative town so if your niche is
simple
you don't have to have a complex
uh world model and something simple like
a world view like a religion
can serve you just fine it might
actually be better because it's the
sense making lens that
simplifies reality
but
if you're
motivated uh and you're someone who
wants to
uh take on you know this
i guess you know
modeling more variables in the world
there will always be
uh niches for you to exploit at places
like academic universities
and corporations where there are these
niches that
create this environment where
there's actually this pressure towards
more complex models and that means these
there will be this evolutionary tendency
towards organisms with a larger
mental repertoire
um so this niche emergence process where
you get these increasingly complex
species you can actually
measure that increase using something
like integrated information theories phi
which measures
basically the size of the mental
repertoire
and uh so that's what
this niche emergence process is doing
it's creating increasingly complex
species that are more intelligent
because they have a larger repertoire of
accessible mental states
but on top of that
you have this other
component of intelligence which relates
to
how the system is reflecting on itself
so you get these emergence of
higher levels
of
awareness and i didn't talk about this
but that's really what the prefrontal
cortex in the brain does it's a module
that unites these other
computational modules which often do
processing
uh individually um there's this global
workspace that emerges
and basically
um that's a meta-system transition as
well so
as far as like
uh
kind of lessons for
society
um
i think uh
you know
part of intelligence is these levels of
awareness where you have consciousness
and then you have self-consciousness or
self-awareness that leads to different
types of
behavior
but then there's another level that you
might call meta awareness and it's
realizing that you're a conscious agent
in a network of conscious agents that
form
this higher level meta system that we
call society
and
um
so uh basically to
uh and i hinted at this during the talk
to overcome our
existential challenges our
sustainability challenges um ensuring
that artificial intelligence
isn't used in this way that destroys
civilization
all of these
big problems require
us coming together and the nations
working cooperatively
because it
solving those problems requires the
computational power of the full system
so we need to
cooperate to
basically exploit this synergistic
effect
that occurs when you work with others
rather than working alone
the other
another thing i guess i'd say right now
about um kind of lessons for society
is that complexity is really a function
of two things
you need a lot of parts um and the parts
need to be
highly connected the more connections
between the parts
and the more diversity there is among
the components
then the more complex that system is and
the more computational power
it can have
so
um
that's basically why you can't have life
emerge if you only have like all
hydrogen elements are all oxygen
elements like you can't just have
like one or two types of atoms you need
um this distribution
of molecules because they play
they function as something like a
division of labor so at the society
level
a society full of
exclusively made of engineers or made of
doctors or made of artists like none of
those societies would be functional if
they had one type of person so you need
a diversity among the component parts
and you want a lot of connections
between those parts so technology that
connects us
not just the internet but social media
and blockchain technology anything that
bypasses middlemen and is starting to
make all these connections between the
units
those things are good they can also be
bad as well
we don't want to
connect in a way where we become some
sort of homogeneous hive mind i know
when i say the global brain a lot of
people express problems with that fears
over becoming this
kind of hive mind which i think china's
government is like
like basically trying to create and they
have this philosophy of that the the
citizens
recognizes that they're part of an
interdependent whole
and they kind of use this to you know
tell people like uh convince people that
like surveillance and all these other
things like you know that take away
freedoms is good because you're doing it
for the greater good
so what this paradigm says is that we
want to become increasingly connected
but we don't want to be homogeneous
because we want diversity among the
component parts and a system like that
especially a system that doesn't allow
criticism
doesn't allow for a diversity of ideas
a system that's homogeneous doesn't
allow for cultural diversity so
diversity
and interconnection is good we want to
come together we want to bring the
nations together but we also want to
keep the
identities of the nations at the same
time we want to preserve the cultures
a brain is
super integrated uh with you know 80
billion neurons and 10 000 connections
between each of those no those neurons
but it's also structured hierarchically
and you have
these different levels of modules and
you have you know
you have like the fusiform face area
processing phases you have like the
visual cortex doing visual stuff all
this all these things
are specialized but they're working
together
and i think that provides a model
for optimizing society
and that
evolutionary principles can inform
how we structure our
governance systems our economic systems
okay
a few more questions if you'd like is
that cool sure yeah all right
so you've mentioned a few things about
the trajectory towards integration
what do you say to
you see that where you see it up until
you don't
and where you don't see it so how do we
really assess what is like
what must happen or what probably
happens given our really limited
knowledge
and how do we sort of balance this
optimization across multiple
points in a design space with this n
equals one trajectory that our one body
one spaceship earth all this sort of
stuff
is um
limited by
in
the
scenario that we're in
yeah so i mean we can't see you know
what we don't know
uh so
i'm definitely not arguing that this
process is inevitable uh in the way that
would make our civilization incapable of
failing
um evolution towards higher progress
occurs
um
because life is always learning from its
mistakes so it's failing
it's failing constantly
and um
i didn't mention this principle in the
book i call it popper's principle but it
says problems create progress so it's a
story of this you know this eternal
thermodynamic challenge of staying far
from equilibrium which requires
extracting energy
um which requires also avoiding threats
and just maintaining the stable state in
the face of uh you know a chaotic and
noisy world
and
um
that uh
yeah it's basically the challenges that
we face that uh force us
to find solutions
um so it's not this straight march of
progress it's not teleological in that
way where there's like nothing stopping
our failure we're actually going to fail
over and over but because there's memory
we learn from our mistakes
um as long as you know that those
failures are encoded in memory in some
way you get this progressive process
and um
as far as like how do we handle like
what we
don't know um we have to actually engage
in this process that
uh i would say is very
bayesian um we have to um
[Music]
try to
imagine all of the possible futures we
have to map out all of the
counterfactuals
because that sort of
allows us to see the possibility space
and if we don't do this we're like
sitting ducks like there's there's no
way for us to be able to handle the
challenges that are coming
and uh
it was interesting like writing the book
um
and thinking about these ideas and you
know going from non-equilibrium
thermodynamics to finding out about like
the free energy principle and that it's
basically
part of this non-equilibrium story like
how systems persist in a universe
abiding by the second law of
thermodynamics
i was talking i was telling a friend
about it
um who was in design school i think it
was parsons design school and they had
this class they were teaching on future
forecasting
and it was literally i guess it was for
people like architects all types of jobs
but their job was to map out like the
different possibilities of reality and
like the different trajectories of ways
we could go and
they had to map out what was like likely
and like less likely and you know at all
these different levels of likelihood
but if one thing if if
current events have showed us anything
it's that
things
don't always happen that we predict
are likely i don't think trump becoming
president
would have seemed likely
10 years ago i don't think
the pandemic i don't think the storming
of the capital would have seemed likely
so
we
actually have to do the work of mapping
out the space of all possible futures
and this is part of planning i mean this
is what good planning does
this is made possible by the prefrontal
cortex we can
uniquely
do this you know
process
because uh we're you know at the leading
edge of intelligence
but
it's it's a practice that we have to
engage in
um
now if we want to be prepared for the
future
awesome
i just wanted to
post this out on a little bit more of a
general or personal note perhaps
wanted to hear your view on how the
writing and the reception of your book
as opposed to say
other live stream appearances or
articles you've written
how did that process of writing the book
update your sense of science's direction
especially in terms of global
participation
and education and research
like where are we at with science
inclusion
participation and
just
where is science going with all these
topics that you thread together
in the work like where does that bundle
of science go
and how to change how did writing the
book update the way that you were seeing
that
yeah so i guess the first thing i would
say was that it became very apparent
especially reading about evolutionary
epistemology and karl popper because his
work was the philosophy of science
and epistemology
and it became really clear that academia
kind of um
you know you you can't think of an idea
like too radical everything you do has
to be based on past research you can't
just
invent a question and you know write a
paper about like
some like if you tried to
submit a paper to a journal that didn't
reference
past work it would not have any chance
of getting accepted
and this is good in a way because it
forces people to read the literature and
understand what's out there
but it's really constraining and you
have this publisher parish game that
makes it such that
people are just going where there's you
know easy publication so uh you're and
you're you're being conservative you
want to just
build very small
incrementally on the work that has come
before but the problem is
that if you have this big integrated
view because you've looked at all of
these different fields like if you look
at
you know from
biology to neuroscience to
thermodynamics to information theory
uh cybernetics um
you're going to be seeing connections
people that are just like biologists
working in the field like and paying
attention to those mainstream biology
journals that they just don't see
and um
there's so so there's not enough
interdisciplinary like connection
collaboration
um there's not enough emphasis there's
not enough appreciation for generalists
like everybody's like um
uh basically pressured to be a
specialist in science and
we really need generalists right now to
step back and look at all the different
fields and not just fields of science
but philosophy
because anytime you do science you're
making philosophical and metaphysical
assumptions
um and
uh
yeah the in the the hardest problems
that you haven't understood like say the
hard problem of consciousness it's
always
philosophy at first that's going to kind
of define like the territory like make
you understand like what what the
problem is like how to approach it so
we need generalists we need scientists
working with philosophers we need
scientists becoming philosophers we need
philosophers caring more about science
and all these mechanisms rather than
just like picking pan psychism as a
stance because it seems cool to you and
then you just defend it for the rest of
your career i also see a lot of
philosophers just picking like
illusionism or something and sticking to
it like
i think that's bad too we should all be
you know
excited about updating our model when
new evidence comes in that um so yeah we
we shouldn't get tied to
any one idea too much and
um not you know there's a role for
specialists i mean
people solve these really hard problems
in their fields because they're just
kind of have this one track mind and
tunnel vision
but
at the time we're at right now to like
make progress and to really like apply
this stuff like to society because
societies are complex adaptive systems
like it's a big mistake to think like
these things can't like these scientific
understanding of like evolutionary
mechanisms and emergence
can't inform like our institutions and
our
sense of morals that's a big mistake
so um
yeah writing it uh that just became very
apparent that
um
and i was lucky enough to have i
mentioned before harold morowitz as a
professor
and he was just someone you know it was
a neuroscience department but he was an
origin of life researcher so you know he
got us like understanding that like we
we had to start thinking about like you
know
energy like free energy and
staying far from equilibrium
that information theory is important and
epistemology um that
and santa fe institute is
you know good place to mention because
their work is interdisciplinary by
nature
and um
so yeah
we need to be that way and we need to
push back on the culture
that like
actually some scientists are threatened
by this and like
the extended evolutionary synthesis like
if you read that guardian article i
mentioned
that you know a lot of these scientists
are saying that we need to extend the
modern synthesis a lot of scientists
were really mad
and insulted by that
and they feel like it's attacking
this sacred thing and some of them might
even you know
claim that some concepts are
pseudoscience i still see people
thinking like emergence like some people
thinking
you know some of these different
concepts from complexity science are
like not real science and a lot of times
those are people that are just
have been like indoctrinated by like uh
militant reductionism i won't like go
like you know talk too bad about
reductionism it's a great method but
it's a terrible
philosophy and worldview
um so
yeah i think there needs to be a big
push to have an awareness
that we need
generalists we need people looking at
everything and i think people who aren't
in academia who are interested in this
kind of stuff people who follow the
channel but they're not like at a
university they have a big role to play
here and they can
you know see these connections and blog
about it whatever they do to like create
content that
kind of shapes the narrative because
that's one thing i've seen like the
narrative does get shaped by culture and
by these people who are really good at
articulating things um daniel
schmucktenberger is kind of like a
complexity theorist philosopher but you
know i as far as i'm aware he doesn't
have like you know he's he's not in
academia
but um people like this are kind of like
showing us these connections and
trying to create a sense-making lens
out of our scientific paradigms and um
i think we're going in the direction i'm
i'm excited to see like i've been
finding all these new communities so i'm
looking for them like metamodern
communities and
game b
and uh these people are looking for this
kind of like integrated
uh paradigms and it's pretty exciting
thanks for the answer just to share a
few more ideas and you can feel free to
respond or we can go as long as you want
so
when you were mentioning
those regimes of attention
which is an active inference term
meaning the regimes of action and
cognitive states like what entities are
doing in the niche and what their
cognitive models are
and in the social context that relates
to the concept of scripts like strong
and weak scripts
and when it comes to science
broadly
that niche and the scripts and the norms
and the archetypes
and all the different players include
like the journals the publishers what
people are paying attention to the
public science meme pages like
everything
and then
i
heard
the call for the normalization of
transdisciplinary collaboration which
implies at least like an island of
shared generalism
like not everyone in the
transdisciplinary collaboration is going
to be
pan generalist but there has to be some
overlap in their venn diagram or some
way that they can align in their
perspectives which is related to
generalism or being able to take
different vistas on the differences
between the perspectives
um and then like that transdisciplinary
collaboration
whether in the mind of one person or on
teams
it happens and and hopefully will happen
at the informal like everyday level
just bringing that kind of curiosity and
synthesis to like well it's really cool
that the algae are growing here next to
the waterfall and not here
what does that mean about
uncertainty or how do they how are they
minimizing free energy by living here
not there so that kind of like everyday
embodied science conversation and then
also hopefully
the rigorous
like decentralized science desai
research
that teams and communities could be
carrying out
so
i just
thought it was kind of cool how this is
a idea that applies to like the whole
continuum
of
what today is occupied by like research
institutions doing research
and then like the
the citizenry and the population
receiving a very certain kind of science
communication and not necessarily like a
including or an engaging one and then
just the last point was i um
heard you talk about pluralism
and this sort of like
bayesian pluralism
like you have a portfolio of models and
maybe
on some features or over some time scale
some fit better than another
but
just one model in a portfolio of models
train like one investing strategy or one
chess move
transiently doing better in a situation
is hardly like
something objective about that strategy
or that chess move it's something that
should be seen in context and across
this distribution of all the chess moves
and so on
so i think that's a really
rich angle
and
that avenue of scientific pluralism
which
helen longino and others have explored
is really
rewarding
because it just speaks to some of those
questions about like
modernism and game b and so on
and resolving the sometimes apparent
tension between
like multiple truths
and scientific pursuit
of what is epistemically good
and so
i guess i'll just close by
giving you the floor for any other
comments you'd like to make and
otherwise just say this was a great
discussion i really appreciate the work
and coming on and sharing
yeah all that you said was great um
totally agree uh and i think these kind
of conversations just you know us
recording this and putting it online and
you creating this channel
um
i think we're seeing you know
all of these things are popping up
partially because the pandemic it was
great that like you know people had to
embrace like zoom
because we were going crazy um being by
ourselves um but yeah i'm seeing so much
excitement
regarding like these kind of questions
like the hard problem of consciousness
like you know origin of life um
[Music]
all of this stuff people
are super excited about to wear like all
you know these people working in these
fields um from science to ai they've
become like celebrities
and it's amazing that
i i saw the kind of progression in the
last few years
where the the kind of the amount of
knowledge of people who weren't in
academia
uh just was like so much higher than it
was before like i would say like
10 years ago being on facebook like
regular people were learning about like
schrodinger's cat and like making jokes
about it and making memes about it and
you know there
were these
specific ideas things that you know
stephen hawking wrote about in a brief
history of time like black holes like
singularities whatever there are all
these topics that were people were like
getting into and like understanding
enough to where they were becoming memes
but like in the last few years i've seen
this like
crazy explosion where like people in
these communities like these like
facebook groups or on twitter i mean
they know a lot they know sometimes like
it seems like they have a lot more
knowledge as far as like the
philosophical context of one like
problem than the actual like experts in
the field and so i think this is great
and people just need to have these
dialogues they need to record them and
put them online and
there needs to be like this like
discussion you know between different
fields different groups um
and yeah it's great that
so
you talked about like you know asked
about the experience writing the book um
i wrote an article called is the
universe pro-life and it really just
argued that um
[Music]
life was inevitable the emergence of
life it wasn't saying anything about the
emergence of intelligence or anything
but um so it was a pretty
it was a pop article but it got into
like thermodynamics on equilibrium
thermodynamics and but it had this like
catchy title is the universe pro-life
and uh sean carroll was nice enough to
give a quote for it and then retweet it
with like an endorsement and i think
that helped
get the book deal
but um so
uh i was pitching it to different
publishers
and
um
[Music]
harvard uh the harvard editor saw that
article and was interested
and we had lunch and i told him about it
but like when he heard like the whole
story and then saw the proposal he was
like this is just like too big i'm not
sure like
which reviewers to get for this because
it's just you know so many different
fields it seemed like very philosophical
to him it was great because then i got
my uh publisher ben bella which
published publishes like pop
science books um
and that gave me the freedom
to
write something like this big in scope
so it's great that popular science books
exist i hope more scientists
you know start writing like stuff like
outside of their field and in journals
um but it was funny because once i wrote
it the you know my agent was like this
is really technical i'm not sure how
it's going to do because it's written at
a college level and like you know
usually pop books are written out like a
high school level
and so it turned out being a book that
probably would have worked for like an
academic press um
but uh
so yeah um i wasn't sure
how it was going to be received
because it had this larger kind of
teleological narrative that was purely
mechanistic um
and uh so far it's been great it was
really surprising that i got people
who people like michael shermer who are
you know known for being
like skeptics and atheists um because
you know they felt that it was
you know the the mechanisms were
articulated well enough to to show that
you know something like this
teleological narrative
uh
was you know legitimate science and uh
something really exciting
um
but it was funny because like
i won't say this person's name but they
were
a famous cosmologist that i thought
would um
be really into the ideas of the book
because it were these ideas of like
emergence and kind of just teleological
stuff and that person was like really
influential in
that kind of niche area but um they said
that they thought that the book was
written you know
super well and
uh
that they thought it would um
be successful but that he couldn't
endorse it because it was
it talked it mentioned too many
reductionists it was like too much
reliant on um
on richard dawkins and dan didn't it so
where i thought it was really going to
appeal to like the spiritual scientists
it was like too reductionistic for them
and then for some maybe reductionist
scientists it was too much like on the
emergent side so
it was it became very clear there was a
culture war
and that we've
been held back from progress
just talking about like a science of
agency
like it an emergence these ideas for
some reductionists like we're too
abstract and not well defined
and we're considered pseudoscience or
like new age stuff or you know whatever
theology
um
so um
both sides have to kind of
see where the other side's coming from
and what they
have to contribute
and i hope the book you know
i wish i would have had a year two more
years to like really make the book what
it was it feels like something that's
like
not complete or something that needs to
be like continually updated because
they're definitely
um
open questions like i forgot to like put
i didn't have time to like address like
the fermi paradox um
stuff that was like really relevant and
hopefully i've talked about in these
talks
but um i was really happy with uh the
way um
you know
people who
are looking for a science book have
embraced and got excited about
this larger story of purpose and
progress
because it totally changes the narrative
it really just
goes from the reductionist worldview
which said you know
life and mind are epic phenomena and we
don't have true agency and that life is
transient it's a really nihilistic
depressing world view
to a scientific world view that does
have spiritual implications we're not
we're not um
uh
we're not these
tren we're not destined for transients
and um one person wrote me and said
something like
um
understanding this worldview made
reality like our like just the general
experience of being alive feel different
feel like more infused with like meaning
and purpose
and that you know would be like
one of the major goals of that is
that you know people don't feel like
life is some sort of fluke or cosmic
accident that were actually a natural
manifestation
of
uh physical laws and
that
um
this actually
it's not just this optimistic picture
that's fun to believe it actually gives
us a picture of where we might be going
and how to deal with that so doing this
thing that i mentioned about like
mapping out all the counter factuals so
we can ensure that
we move along the trajectory that's
consistent with the continual
existence and
progression of life
so yeah let's let's open our arms to
philosophy and metaphysics and anything
that can
inform the scientific picture because
science needs philosophy
amazing bobby thank you again for this
and really appreciate the time and we'll
plan
point three when the time is right yeah
so good luck with everything and see you
around
thank you so much daniel love the
questions thanks for everybody else who
uh
is in the chat or whatever
appreciate it
all right thank you
have a good
you